of this democracy, and it's not a flaw every one out of 360 billion times our democracy tries to make a decision. It is every time, every single important issue. We've got to end the bovinity of this political society. We've got to adopt, it turns out, the word is fourmi-formatic attitude -- that's what the Internet tells me the word is -- the ant's appreciative attitude that gets us to recognize this flaw, save our kind and save our demos. Now if you know Aaron Swartz, you know that we lost him just over a year ago. It was about six weeks before I gave my TED Talk, and I was so grateful to Chris that he asked me to give this TED Talk, not because I had the chance to talk to you, although that was great, but because it pulled me out of an extraordinary depression. I couldn't begin to describe the sadness. Because I had to focus. I had to focus on, what was I going to say to you? It saved me. But after the buzz, the excitement, the power that comes from this community, I began to yearn for a less sterile, less academic way to address these issues, the issues that I was talking about. We'd begun to focus on New Hampshire as a target for this political movement, because the primary in New Hampshire is so incredibly important. It was a group called the New Hampshire Rebellion that was beginning to talk about, how would we make this issue of this corruption central in 2016? But it was another soul that caught my imagination, a woman named Doris Haddock, aka Granny D. On January 1, 1999, 15 years ago, at the age of 88, Granny D started a walk. She started in Los Angeles and began to walk to Washington, D.C. with a single sign on her chest that said, "campaign finance reform." Eighteen months later, at the age of 90, she arrived in Washington with hundreds following her, including many congressmen who had gotten in a car and driven out about a mile outside of the city to walk in with her. (Laughter) Now, I don't have 13 months to walk across the country. I've got three kids who hate to walk, and a wife who, it turns out, still hates when I'm not there for mysterious reasons, so this was not an option, but the question I asked, could we remix Granny D a bit? What about a walk not of 3,200 miles but of 185 miles across New Hampshire in January? So on January 11, the anniversary of Aaron's death, we began a walk that ended on January 24th, the day that Granny D was born. A total of 200 people joined us across this walk, as we went from the very top to the very bottom of New Hampshire talking about this issue. And what was astonishing to me, something I completely did not expect to find, was the passion and anger that there was among everyone that we talked to about this issue. We had found in a poll that 96 percent of Americans believe it important to reduce the influence of money in politics. Now politicians and pundits tell you, there's nothing we can do about this issue, Americans don't care about it, but the reason for that is that 91 percent of Americans think there's nothing that can be done about this issue. And it's this gap between 96 and 91 that explains our politics of resignation. I mean, after all, at least 96 percent of us wish we could fly like Superman, but because at least 91 percent of us believe we can't, we don't leap off of tall buildings every time we have that urge. That's because we accept our limits, and so too with this reform. But when you give people the sense of hope, you begin to thaw that absolute sense of impossibility. As Harvey Milk said, if you give 'em hope, you give 'em a chance, a way to think about how this change is possible. Hope. And hope is the one thing that we, Aaron's friends, failed him with, because we let him lose that sense of hope. I loved that boy like I love my son. But we failed him. And I love my country, and I'm not going to fail that. I'm not going to fail that. That sense of hope, we're going to hold, and we're going to fight for, however impossible this battle looks. What's next? Well, we started with this march with 200 people, and next year, there will be 1,000 on different routes that march in the month of January and meet in Concord to celebrate this cause, and then in 2016, before the primary, there will be 10,000 who march across that state, meeting in Concord to celebrate this cause. And as we have marched, people around the country have begun to say, "Can we do the same thing in our state?" So we've started a platform called G.D. Walkers, that is, Granny D walkers, and Granny D walkers across the country will be marching for this reform. Number one. Number two, on this march, one of the founders of Thunderclap, David Cascino, was with us, and he said, "Well what can we do?" And so they developed a platform, which we are announcing today, that allows us to pull together voters who are committed to this idea of reform. Regardless of where you are, in New Hampshire or outside of New Hampshire, you can sign up and directly be informed where the candidates are on this issue so you can decide who to vote for as a function of which is going to make this possibility real. And then finally number three, the hardest. We're in the age of the Super PAC. Indeed yesterday, Merriam announced that Merriam-Webster will have Super PAC as a word. It is now an official word in the dictionary. So on May 1, aka May Day, we're going to try an experiment. We're going to try a launching of what we can think of as a Super PAC to end all Super PACs. And the basic way this works is this. For the last year, we have been working with analysts and political experts to calculate, how much would it cost to win enough votes in the United States Congress to make fundamental reform possible? What is that number? Half a billion? A billion? What is that number? And then whatever that number is, we are going to kickstart, sort of, because you can't use KickStarter for political work, but anyway, kickstart, sort of, first a bottom-up campaign where people will make small dollar commitments contingent on reaching very ambitious goals, and when those goals have been reached, we will turn to the large dollar contributors, to get them to contribute to make it possible for us to run the kind of Super PAC necessary to win this issue, to change the way money influences politics, so that on November 8, which I discovered yesterday is the day that Aaron would have been 30 years old, on November 8, we will celebrate 218 representatives in the House and 60 Senators in the United States Senate who have committed to this idea of fundamental reform. So last night, we heard about wishes. Here's my wish. May one. May the ideals of one boy unite one nation behind one critical idea that we are one people, we are the people who were promised a government, a government that was promised to be dependent upon the people alone, the people, who, as Madison told us, meant not the rich more than the poor. May one. And then may you, may you join this movement, not because you're a politician, not because you're an expert, not because this is your field, but because if you are, you are a citizen. Aaron asked me that. Now I've asked you. Thank you very much. (Applause)
de esta democracia, y no es un defecto que ocurra cada 360 000 millones de veces que nuestra democracia trata de tomar una decisión. Ocurre cada vez, en cada tema importante. Tenemos que terminar con esta sociedad política bovina. Tenemos que adoptar una actitud mirmicina, Internet dice que esta es la palabra, la actitud apreciativa de las hormigas que nos permite reconocer este defecto, salvar a nuestra especie, a nuestro demos. Si conocen a Aaron Swartz, saben que lo perdimos hace un año. Fueron unas 6 semanas antes de dar mi charla TED, y le agradezco mucho a Chris que me pidiera dar esta charla TED, no por poder hablar ante Uds., aunque eso fuera genial, sino porque me sacaba de una gran depresión. No podía describir esa tristeza porque tenía que concentrarme. Tenía que concentrarme en lo que les diría a Uds. Eso me salvó. Después de los murmullos, del entusiasmo, del poder surgido de esta comunidad, empecé a anhelar una manera menos estéril, menos académica de abordar estos temas, los temas de los que estaba hablando. Empezamos a centrarnos en Nueva Hampshire como destino de este movimiento político, porque las primarias de Nueva Hampshire son realmente cruciales. Había un grupo llamado Rebelión de Nueva Hampshire que empezó a plantear cómo poner en el centro este tema de la corrupción en 2016. Pero otro ser cautivó mi imaginación, una mujer llamada Doris Haddock, alias abuelita D. El 1 de enero de 1999, hace 15 años, a los 88 años, la abuelita D empezó a caminar. Empezó en Los Ángeles y empezó a caminar hasta Washington, DC, con un cartel en el pecho que decía: "Reforma al financiamiento de campañas políticas". 18 meses después, a los 90 años, llegó a Washington, seguida por cientos de personas, incluyendo muchos congresistas que llegaron en auto a menos de 2 km de la llegada para caminar con ella. (Risas) Yo no tengo 13 meses para caminar por el país. Tengo 3 niños que detestan caminar, y una esposa que detesta cuando me ausento por razones misteriosas. Por eso no era una opción, pero me pregunté si podíamos imitar un poco a la abuelita D. ¿Y si caminamos no 5000 km sino 300 km por Nueva Hampshire en enero? Así, el 11 de enero, el aniversario de la muerte de Aaron, empezamos una caminata que terminó el 24 de enero, día de nacimiento de la abuelita D. Unas 200 personas se sumaron a esta marcha, conforme recorrimos Nueva Hampshire de arriba abajo hablando de este tema. Y lo sorprendente para mí, algo que no esperaba encontrar, fue la pasión y la ira compartida por las personas con las que hablamos del tema. Mediante una encuesta vimos que el 96 % de los estadounidenses creen importante reducir la influencia del dinero en la política. Los políticos y los expertos dicen que no puede hacerse nada, que en EE.UU. no se preocupan, pero debido a que 91 % de los estadounidenses cree que no se puede hacer nada. Y esta brecha entre 96 % y 91 % explica nuestra política de resignación. Digo, después de todo, al menos el 96 % desearíamos poder volar como Súperman, pero como al menos el 91 % creemos que no podemos volar, no saltamos de los edificios altos cuando sentimos la necesidad. Porque aceptamos nuestros límites, y lo mismo ocurre con esta reforma. Pero cuando le damos esperanza a la gente, empieza a diluirse esa imposibilidad absoluta. Como dijo Harvey Milk, si les damos esperanza, les damos una oportunidad, una forma de pensar en la posibilidad de este cambio. Esperanza. Y esperanza es lo que nosotros, los amigos de Aaron, le negamos, porque hicimos que perdiera esa esperanza. Amo a ese muchacho, como amo a mi hijo. Pero le fallamos. Y amo a mi comunidad, y no le voy a fallar. No le voy a fallar. Mantendremos viva esa esperanza y lucharemos por ella, sin importar lo difícil que parezca la batalla. ¿Qué sigue? Bueno, empezamos con esta marcha de 200 personas, y el año próximo, habrá 1000 en distintas rutas que marcharán en enero y se concentrarán en Concord para celebrar esta causa y luego en 2016, antes de las primeras, marcharán 10 000 personas por el estado, y se reunirán en Concord a celebrar esta causa. Y conforme marchábamos, en todo el país nos preguntaban: "¿Podemos hacer lo mismo en nuestro estado?" Así que lanzamos una plataforma llamada G.D. Walkers, o sea "Granny D Walkers" [caminantes abuela D] y habrá caminantes de la abuela D en todo el país marchando por esta reforma. En primer lugar. Segundo, en esta marcha, uno de los fundadores de Thunderclap, David Cascino, estaba con nosotros, y dijo: "¿Qué podemos hacer?" Así que desarrollaron una plataforma que anunciamos hoy, que nos permite reunir a los votantes comprometidos con esta idea de reforma. Independientemente de dónde se encuentren, dentro o fuera de Nueva Hampshire, pueden registrarse y recibir información de las posturas de los candidatos sobre este tema para poder decidir por quién votar de acuerdo a quién hará realidad esta posibilidad. Y para terminar, número tres, lo más difícil. Es la era del comité de acción política (Súper PAC) De hecho, ayer, Merriam anunció que acuñará la expresión "Súper PAC". Ahora es una expresión oficial del diccionario. El 1 de mayo, alias May Day, haremos un experimento. Vamos a lanzar una acción política que creemos es un Súper PAC para poner fin a los Súper PACs. Y esto funciona así. El último año hemos estado trabajando con analistas y expertos políticos para calcular cuánto costaría juntar suficientes votos para una victoria en el Congreso de EE.UU. y hacer así posible la reforma. ¿Cuánto? ¿USD 500 millones? ¿USD 1000 millones? ¿Cuánto? Y luego, cualquiera sea la suma, lanzaremos un financiamiento colaborativo propio porque no se puede usar KickStarter con fines políticos, como sea, un financiamiento colaborativo, primero una campaña en las bases donde las personas contribuirán con pequeñas sumas supeditadas a lograr objetivos muy ambiciosos y cuando se logren esos objetivos, pasaremos a los grandes contribuyentes, para hacer que contribuyan a hacer posible que ejecutemos las acciones políticas para ganar en este tema, y cambiar la influencia del dinero en la política. El 8 de noviembre, ayer lo descubrí, es el día que Aaron cumpliría 30 años, el 8 de noviembre, celebraremos 218 representantes en la Cámara y 60 en el Senado, en el Senado de EE.UU., comprometidos con esta idea de reforma estructural. Anoche escuchamos deseos. Este es mi deseo. Mayo [May] "1". Puedan [May] los ideales de "1" muchacho unir a una Nación detrás de una idea crucial de que somos un solo pueblo, somos el pueblo al que se le prometió un gobierno, un gobierno que prometieron dependería única y solamente del pueblo, que, como nos dijo Madison, que un rico no valga más que un pobre. "May 1" [Mayo 1, Pueda uno]. Ojalá puedan sumarse a este movimiento, no porque sean políticos, no porque sean expertos, no porque sea su campo, sino porque si existen, son ciudadanos. Aaron me lo pidió. Ahora se los pido yo a Uds. Muchas gracias. (Aplausos)